Music, Vocal and Instrumental, Associated with New Haven
Yale University Music Library
Music, Vocal and Instrumental, Associated with New Haven
1775-1972
Misc. Ms. 365
Yale University Music Library
1
(2 boxes)
Music, programs, and other items associated with New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Music Library
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: I. Music. II. Programs. III. Articles.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of musical scores associated with New Haven, Connecticut in various ways; for example, some have lyrics that mention New Haven or Yale, others were written by New Haven composers, and still others were published in New Haven. The collection also includes 111 concert programs (dating from 1860 to 1970), a 1941 newspaper article about the history of music in New Haven, and a list of New Haven references in Musical Review.
Music, instrumental and vocal, associated with New Haven
- Music, Series I
  - Father almighty: A hymn for four or six voices / by Asahel Abbot; words by the late Miss Martha Day. -- New York: Firth, Pond & Hall, [n.d.], Abbot, Asahel; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Inscribed to Rev. Jeremiah Day, D.D.
    For four or six voices and organ.
  - Alma mater O: An American student-song. -- New York: Richard Storrs Willis, c1855., 1 score ([4] p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    As sung at Yale College, on Presentation Day.
    For 3 voices and piano.
  - Troop A: A calvary march and two step / by Geo. L. Atwater Jr. -- New Haven, Conn.: C.F. Smith, c1910., Atwater, George L., Jr.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    For piano.
  - Away the bowl (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Warren, Charles J. The temperance harp.
  - Triumphal march / by Enrico Batelli. -- New Haven, Conn.: [s.n.], c1929., Batelli, Enrico; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The grapevine swing: Song / music by C.C. Benham; words by S. Minturn Peck. -- New Haven, Conn.: Treat & Shepard Co., c1890., Benham, C.C.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Dedicated to Miss Dora Waldo of Hudson, N.Y.
    For voice and piano.
  - Stand by the flag: New Haven Kiwanis liberty song / words and music by Clarence E. Billings. -- New Haven, Conn.: K. Music Co., c1918., Billings, Clarence E.; 1 score (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    2 copies
  - Yum tum tum / words and music by Ben Bronfin. -- New Haven, Conn.: Peter C. Caporossi, c1921., Bronfin, Ben; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jubilee / Oliver Brownson., Brownson, Oliver; 1 manuscript score (1 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copy.
    "From: The chorister's companion - S. Jocelin...New Haven, 1788."
    Printed on the same leaf as Mear / Andrew Law. "From: the Art of singing, Part II by Andrew Law, A.M. Printed and sold by William Law, Cheshire, 1794."
    2 photocopies of manuscript
    For 4 voices.
  - Virginia, Brownson, Oliver (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Music by composers from New Haven County 1770-1825.
  - You are the rose (I'm longing for): Ballad, Caporossi, Peter C. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Romney, Ted C.
  - Co-ca-che-lunk. -- New York: R. Storrs Willis, c1855., 1 score ([4] p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    A student song as sung at Yale College on Presentation day.
    For voice and acc.
  - Col. Bellamy's march (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Marches.
  - Cold water army (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cold water army pledge (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Il Primo incontro: Waltzes = The first meeting / composed by I. Curti; arr. by C. Caramano. -- Philadelphia: J. Starr Holloway, Publisher, c1869., Curti, I., arr. Caramano, C.; 1 score (141 [i.e. 4] p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Dedicated to Miss Justine Ingersoll, New Haven, Conn.
    Bound with Jones, Maurice D.: Sunset on the mountains hoary.
  - Amelia, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Amelia: for 2 violins, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Duettino-Rondo-Jigg, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Duetto for two violins, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Duetto for two violins or two flutes, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jefferson's march, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - March in a midnight serenade, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - March in a midnight serenade, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - March of the disbanded troops, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - March of the disbanded troops: for 2 violins, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Warren's march, Curtiss, John F. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Elm-city waltzes / composed by Anthony J. Davis. -- New Haven, Conn.: C.M. Brocksieper, c1883., Davis, Anthony J.; 1 score (9 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Introduction -- No. 1 -- 2 -- 3.
  - The equilibre: Polka-mazurka elegant / by Anthony J. Davis. -- New York: Clayton Music Engraving and Printing Co., c1883., Davis, Anthony J.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Composed expressly for the opening of the genuine "Mathushek" piano warerooms, 257 Chapel St., New Haven, Conn.
  - Thespian Waltz / composed by Anthony J. Davis. -- New Haven, Conn.: C.M. Brocksieper, c1883., Davis, Anthony J.; 1 score (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Dedicated to The Thespian Club, New Haven, Conn.
  - Drink that's in the drunkard's bowl, The (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The house of old Yale / Henry S. Durand., Durand, Henry S.; 1 manuscript score (1 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Copy of holograph.
    Written in 1881? inscribed by the composer in 1923.
  - Happy new year: Gavotte for the piano / music by Ernesto Fasano. -- New Haven, Conn.: Chas. F. Smith, c1911., Fasano, Ernesto; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Dedicated to Café-Mellone, New Haven, Conn.
  - An anthem: from Isaiah xxiv. 17-xxxv. 1, 2 / music composed by Rev. E.T. Fitch; words selected by Rev. L. Bacon. -- New Haven: William Storer, 1838., Fitch, Rev. E.T.; 1 score (8 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Composed for and sung at the celebration of the 2nd centennial anniversary of the settlement of New Haven, April 25, 1838.
    For chorus and instrumental acc.
  - Sugar coated love, Francis, William S. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Willman, Madalen.
  - Edna from New Haven / words and music by Jack Freedman; arr. by P.B. Metcalf. -- Boston: Metcalf Music Co., c1908., Freedman, Jack, arr. Metcalf, P.B.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Score is worn.
  - Il Sorriso: Waltz for piano = The smile / by J. Edward Geary. -- New Haven, Conn.: Socin & Geary, c1891., Geary, J. Edward; 1 score (7 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Photocopy.
  - Fugue / composed by J.E. Goodson. -- [S.l.]: [s.n.], [n.d.], Goodson, J.E.; 1 score (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Music is torn.
    Cover title: "Uncle Jack's Fugue."
    Note in pencil on the cover: "From the Ives family."
  - Gaffer Gray: An old English ballad / by Holcroft; arr. for the piano forte by Frank C. Smith. -- New York: S. T. Gordon, c1856., Holcroft, Thomas, arr. Smith, Frank C.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Dedicated to the Masonic fraternity of New Haven, CT by Frank C. Smith.
  - Connecticut: Song of the Connecticut State Federation of Music Clubs / words and music by Clayton E. Hotchkiss. -- New Haven, Conn.: The Connecticut State Federation of Music Clubs, c1932., Hotchkiss, Clayton Eugene; 1 score (3 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gen'l King's quick step / composed and arr. by James M. Hubbard. -- New York: Wm. Hall & Son, c1848., Hubbard, James M.; 1 score (4 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    As performed at the Govenor's [sic] inauguration (3rd May 1848) in New Haven, Conn. by Bloomfield's "United States Band."
    2 copies.
  - New Haven gray's grand march / composed and arr. for the piano forte by James M. Hubbard. -- New Haven, Conn.: Lyman Biard, c1846., Hubbard, James M.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Haven gray's grand march / composed and arr. for the piano forte by J.M. Hubbard. -- 3rd edition. -- New York: S.T. Gordon; New Haven: Skinner & Sperry, c1861., Hubbard, James M.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Music worn.
  - Dear 'eighty-eight: Solo, duet, quartet and chorus / by B. Jepson; written by Fannie B. Barney and Elizabeth S. Bradley. -- [S.l.]: [s.n.], [n.d.]., Jepson, B.; 1 score ([2] p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Composed for and dedicated to the class of '88, Hillhouse High School, New Haven, CT.
    Piano acc.
  - Sunset on the mountains hoary: Song / by Maurice D. Jones; poetry by Rose Terry. -- Philadelphia: J. Starr Holloway, Publisher, c1868., Jones, Maurice D.; 1 score ([3] p.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Bound with Curti, I. "Il primo incontro: Waltzes."
  - Above and below, Juch, Justin (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Shoninger musical monthly.
  - Les charmes de New Haven!: Rondino à la valse for the piano forte or harp / by Chas. M. King. -- New Haven, Conn.: F. Croswell, [1836]., King, Charles M.; 1 photostat score (8 p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notes on the composer laid in.
  - In peace, love tunes the shepherd's reed: Pastorale / music composed by Charles M. King; the words by Sir Walter Scott. -- New Haven, Conn.: Wm. Storer, c1835., King, Charles M.; 1 score (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Presented, by the author, to the editor of the Literary Emporium, New Haven.
  - Lauriger Horatius: A German student-song. -- New Haven, Conn.: Skinner & Sperry, c1856., 1 score ([4] p.) -- (Student-songs; No. 7.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Arranged as a solo with piano and also as a quartet for 2 tenors and 2 basses.
    "As sung by the students of Yale College."
  - American hero: Bunker Hill / music by Andrew Law., Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1 manuscript score + 1 manuscript part.
    Holograph.
    4 copies of holograph score + 1 part for soprano.
    Typed copy of the text laid in.
  - American hero (Bunker Hill): a Sapphick ode, Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Archdale, Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mear, Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    See Brownson, Oliver. Jubliee.
  - Mear, Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sunbury, Law, Andrew, 1749-1821 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Marches], 1 manuscript score + 6 manuscript parts. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Jefferson's march / John F. Curtiss, Cheshire ca. 1800 -- Warren's march / John F. Curtiss ca. 1800 -- March of the disbanded troops / John Curtiss -- Duetto for 2 violins or 2 flutes / John F. Curtiss -- March in a midnight serenade / John Curtiss -- Amelia / John Curtiss -- Duettino-Rondo-Jigg / John F. Curtiss -- Col. Bellamy's March / from the Bellamy Band Book, Hamden, 1799 -- New Haven march / from the Bellamy Band Book -- Yankee Doodle / version found in the Bellamy Band Book.
    Score is for the New Haven march only. Parts are for 2 violins, 2 flutes, clarinet and bass. Clarinet and bass parts have only the pieces from the Bellamy Band book, flute parts have all but the Duettino and the Duetto. Violin parts have all the pieces.
  - Margaret's bridal (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - March no. 1 (To the White House): Scotch air / music arr. by Major John McCarthy; words by Dr. Creamer Peckham. -- New Haven, Conn.: A. B. Clinton Co., c1908., McCarthy, John; 1 score ([3] p.) -- (Campaign songs: Hon. William Howard Taft.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    March no. 1 (To the White House) -- No. 2 -- No. 3.
    Paper is worn.
  - March no. 2 (To the White House): German air / music arr. by Major John McCarthy; words by Dr. Creamer Peckham. -- New Haven, Conn.: A. B. Clinton Co., [n.d.]., McCarthy, John; 1 score ([3] p.) -- (Campaign songs: Hon. William Howard Taft.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    March no. 2 (To the White House) -- No. 5 -- No. 6.
  - Lord forever at thy side / composed by Wm. W. Moses. -- New Haven, Conn.: Skinner & Sperry, c1869., Moses, Wm. W.; 1 score (7 p.) -- (Sacred quartettes composed by W.W. Moses.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Text is from Psalm 195.
    Arranged for quartet of mixed voices and organ.
    Obituaries of W. Moses pasted to the inside of the cover.
  - Music by composers from New Haven County, 1770-1825; 1 manuscript score ([10] p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Mear / Andrew Law -- Sunbury / Andrew Law -- Mear / attr. to Andrew Law, from Andrew Law's The art of singing, Cheshire, 1794 -- Mear / attr. to Andrew Law / Virginia / Oliver Brownson, from Chorister's Companion, New Haven, 1788 -- Amelia: for 2 violins / J. Curtiss, Cheshire ca. 1800 -- March of the disbanded troops: for 2 violins / J. Curtiss, Cheshire, ca. 1800 -- March in a midnight serenade / John Curtiss, Cheshire, ca. 1800 -- Archdale / Andrew Law, from the Christian Harmony, or the second part of the Art of singing, Cheshire 1794 -- Windham / Daniel Read -- Duetto for 2 violins / John Curtiss, Cheshire, ca. 1800 -- The American hero or Bunker Hill: A Sapphick ode / Nathaniel Niles -- The American hero or Bunker Hill: A Sapphick ode/ Nathaniel Niles; arr. by Andrew Law, 1775.
    Collection songs for four voices and instrumental works.
  - My heart's in old Ireland: A ballad. -- Philadelphia: J.C. Smith, c1848., 1 score (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Music composed and dedicated to Mrs. Genl. Gaines by a Lady of New Haven.
  - New Haven march (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American hero (Bunker Hill): a Sapphick ode, Niles, Nathaniel (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oh, wild is the path (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sugar coated love, Platzman, Eugene (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Son tutto tuo: Romanza / musica e parole di Giovanni Porto. -- New Haven, Conn.: Giovanni Porto, c1917., Porto, Giovanni; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pity the homeless one to-night: Song and chorus / music by Charles E. Pratt; words by George Cooper. -- [New Haven, Conn.]: [ Wm. A Pond], c1878., Pratt, Charles E.; 1 score ([2] p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Paper is brittle.
  - Providence / Read., Read, Daniel, 1757-1836 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1 manuscript score.
    From the Chorister's Companion. New Haven, 1788.
  - Windham, Read, Daniel, 1757-1836 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - You are the rose (I'm longing for): Ballad / words and music by Ted C. Romney and Peter C. Caporossi. -- Operatic edition. -- New Haven, Conn.: Ryan & Caporossi, c1920., Romney, Ted C. and Caporossi, Peter C.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rule, temperance, rule (Box 1, Folder 4)
    See Warren, Charles J. The Temperance harp.
  - Spinning wheel: Etude-polka = Mon petit rouet, Schmoll, Anton (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - When first I slipp'd my leading strings / composed by Mr. Shield. -- [S.l.]: [s.n.], [n.d.]., Shield, Mr.; 1 score (1 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2 photostat copies.
  - Shoninger Musical Monthly: No. 69. -- New Haven, Conn.: B. Shoninger & Co., 1890., 16 p.: music. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes: 1. Above and below: Song for mezzo soprano or baritone, and mixed chorus / music by Justin Juch; words by Jennie Stovin. -- c1872. 2. Spinning wheel: Etude-polka = Mon petit rouet / Anton Schmoll, op. 7.
  - The New Haven March: for the piano forte / composed by P.A. Smith. -- New York: E. Riley & Co., c1839., Smith, Peter A.; 1 score (2 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Stained.
  - You are my affinity: Barn dance / words and music by Jas. W. Stanford. -- New Haven, Conn.: James W. Stanford, c1908., Stanford, James W.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Toi = For you / music by Rudolph Steinert; words by Lillian Gertrude Shuman. -- New Haven, Conn.: M. Steinert & Sons, c1899., Steinert, Rudolph; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For medium voice and piano.
  - Passing away / by Mrs. Hemans; music composed and arr. for the piano forte by Mrs. Townshend Stith. -- New Haven, Conn.: [s.n.], [n.d.]., Stith, Townshend, Mrs.; 1 score (6 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Dedicated to Miss Anne Murdoch.
  - The dream boat / music by George Chadwick Stock; poem by Bayard Bacon. -- New Haven, Conn.: Treat and Shepard Co., c1906., Stock, George Chadwick; 1 score ([3] p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Dedicated to Miss Grace E. Walker of New Haven, Conn.
  - Sons of Eli: A Yale song / music by George Chadwick Stock; words by D.L. Jacobus. -- New Haven, Conn. :Treat and Shepard Co., c1906., Stock, George Chadwick; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Crambambuli: op. 5 no. 2 / by Gustave J. Stoeckel. -- New York: P.K. Weizel, c1858., Stoeckel, Gustav Jakob, 1819-1907; 1 score (9 p.) -- (Songs of Germany: Paraphrases for the piano; No. 2.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Composed and dedicated to the ladies of Miss. M. Dutton's female seminary, New Haven.
  - Farewell / Gustave J. Stoeckel. -- New York: Wm. A. Pond, c1877., Stoeckel, Gustav Jakob, 1819-1907; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sung by the young ladies at the closing exercises at Grove Hall, New Haven Conn., June 20, 1877.
    Dedicated to Miss Jessie Churchill.
    Score is torn.
    For 2 sopranos, alto, and piano.
  - Tee-total union (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The blushing rose, Trowbridge, Asa R. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Crystal spring, Trowbridge, Asa R. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 'Twas the night before Christmas / tune by Bertha Chadwick Trowbridge; [text] by Clement C. Moore. -- [New Haven, Conn]: [Yale University Press (p)], c1924., Trowbridge, Bertha Chadwick; 1 score ([3] p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For solo voice.
  - The temperance harp: original and selected music, designed to accompany the Temperance hymn book and minstrel by Rev. John Marsh / adapted to be used in social circles, schools, and public meetings by Charles J. Warren. -- New Haven, Conn.: Hitchcock & Stafford (p), 1842., Warren, Charles J.; 1 score ([16] p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Rule, temperance, rule / words from Temp. hymn book, music adapted -- Hurrah, for bright water / words adapted, music by C.J. Warren -- Speed, speed the temperance ship / words from Temp. hymn book, music by C.J. Warren -- Tee-total union -- Oh, wild is the path -- The first pledge / words from Temp. hymn book, music by C.J. Warren -- The blushing rose / words by Charles Thurber, Esq., music by Asa R. Trowbridge -- Crystal spring / words by Charles Thurber, Esq., music by Asa R. Trowbridge -- The drink that's in the drunkard's bowl -- Cheerily, cheerily / words from the Temp. hymn book, music by C.J. Warren -- Away the bowl -- Cold water army -- The Connecticut cold water army / words from the Temp. hymn book, music by C.J. Warren / Drink from the bubbling fountain / words by Theobold Matthew, music by C.J. Warren -- Margaret's bridal / from the Wesleyan harp -- He signs the pledge / words adapted, music by C.J. Warren -- We've burst the chain -- Cold water army pledge.
    For 2, 3, and 4 voices and accompaniment.
  - Souvenir de la harpe éolienne: Nocturne / R.K. Wehner. -- [Boston]: [Oliver Ditson & Co.], [n.d.], Wehner, R.K.; 1 score (9 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    To the young ladies of Miss Nott's School, New Haven, Conn.
    Plate no. 48730.
  - We've burst the chain (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - You just you / Composed by Albert A. Williams; words by Smailliw A. Trebla. -- New Haven, Conn: Albert A. Williams, c1909., Williams, Albert A.; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Married miseries / Richard Storrs Willis; words by Charles Cotton. -- New York: New York Musical World, c1856., Willis, Richard Storrs; 1 score (20 [i.e. 4] p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printed in New York Musical World.
  - Sugar coated love / Madalen Willman, William S. Francis, and Eugene Platzman. -- New Haven, Conn.: Francis and Willman, c1930., Willman, Madalen and Francis, William S. and Platzman, Eugene; 1 score (5 p.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Native Bahamian memories / by Esau Wood and A.F. Fiorillo. -- New Haven, Conn.: A.F. Fiorillo, c1924., Wood, Esau Fiorillo, A.F.; 1 score (7 p.) -- (First series.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Slide Mungo slide -- Spare me one more year -- My lima bean -- Do Aun' Nanny do -- Ballymena -- H'is up the John B. sail.
  - Yankee Doodle (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Programs, Series II
  - 1860-1899, 5 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1900-1909, 4 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1910-1919, 4 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1920-1929, 5 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1950-1959, 23 items (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1960-1965, 41 items (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1966-1970, 29 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Articles, Series III
  - "Musical notes in New Haven History" New Haven Register, Sunday, Nov. 9, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - List of New Haven references in Musical Review (under its various titles), dated 3/13/72 (Box 2, Folder 9)